Jacob Kainen
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
- Correspondence/Subject Files, 1936-2003, undated, Series 2:; (Boxes 1-10; 9.7 linear feet)
  - Gilkey, Gordon W. (see also Pacific Northwest College of Art), 1971-2000, undated, (4 folders) (Box 4)
  - Gilliam, Sam, Jr., 1976-1999, undated (Box 4)
  - Goddard, Stephen, 1998-2001 (Box 4)
  - Gorky, Arshile (see also Fielding, Mrs. A.W.), 1969-1993, undated, (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Gottlieb, Adolph, 1964-1988 (Box 4)
  - Graffman, Gary and Naomi, 1974-1992, undated (Box 4)
  - Greenberg, Amy, 1980-1981 (Box 4)
  - Greenberg, Clement, 1972-1993, (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Greenwald, Bernard (contains handmade cards), 1972-1999, undated, (5 folders) (Box 4)
  - Griffith, Mr. and Mrs. Fuller, 1953-1979 (Box 4)
  - Griffiths, Antony V. (see also British Museum), 1983-2003, undated, (11 folders) (Box 4)
  - Groschwitz, Gustave von, 1973-1990 (Box 4)
  - Guston, Philip, 1971-2000, undated (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous G: Gagosian-Gilmour, 1967-2000, undated (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous G: Glackens-Graham, 1954-1998 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous G: Grana-Gumpert, 1953-2001, undated (Box 4)
  - Halesz, Piri, 1980-2002, undated, (5 folders) (Box 4)
  - Halfant, Jules, 1980-1997, undated (Box 4)
  - Handler, Mr. and Mrs. George R., 1960-1972 (Box 4)
  - Harrison, Carol (contains photographs), 1986-2002, undated, (5 folders) (Box 4)
  - Hart, Harold, 1967-1999, undated (Box 4)
  - Hayter, S.W., 1979-2002, (5 folders) (Box 4)
  - Higginson, Genevra (see also National Gallery of Art), 1990-1999, undated (Box 4)
  - High Museum of Art: see Vigtel, Gudmund (Box 4)
  - Hines, Mr. and Mrs. Felrath, 1975-1999 (Box 4)
  - Hiratsuka, Un-ichi, 1995-2001, undated (Box 4)
  - Hirschl & Alder Galleries, Inc., 1987-2001, undated (Box 4)
  - Hirshhorn Museum and Sculpture Garden (see also Millard, Charles W.), 1975-1999, undated (Box 5)
  - Hitch, Ken and Kiyo, 1989-2000, undated (Box 5)
  - Holden, Donald, 1968-2002, (3 folders) (Box 5)
  - Holladay, Mrs. Wilhelmina (Billie), 1977-2001, undated, (3 folders) (Box 5)
  - Holladay, Winton Smoot, 1978-1995, undated (Box 5)
  - Hom, Jem and Betty, 1970-2001, undated (Box 5)
  - Hoover, J. Edgar: see Smithsonian Institution Loyalty Board (Box 5)
  - Hopps, Walter, 1975-2002, undated (Box 5)
  - Hudson, Andrew, 1974-1985 (Box 5)
  - Hunterian Museum and Art Gallery, 1995 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous H: Haas-Hayes, 1968-1998, undated (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous H: Heller-Hitchings, 1953-2002, undated (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous H: Hoffman-Hynes, 1973-2001, undated (Box 5)
  - Independent Curators Incorporated, 1972-1982, undated, (4 folders) (Box 5)
  - Internal Revenue Service, 1949-1992, (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous I: Iglicki-Istomin, 1955-1999, undated (Box 5)
  - Jackson, John Baptist, 1954-1964, undated, (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - James Smithson Society, 1977-1980 (Box 5)
  - Jewish Community Center of Greater Washington, 1980-1985, undated (Box 5)
  - Joachim, Harold, 1977-1982, undated (Box 5)
  - Johnson, Una E., 1973-1981 (Box 5)
  - Jordon, Jim, 1975-1982, undated, (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Julian, Ruth Reece, 1967-1996 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous J: Jacks-Jessup, 1978-2002, undated (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous J: Jewish Community Center of Greater Baltimore-Juscik, 1974-1992, undated (Box 5)
  - Kainen, Bertha, 1956-2000, undated, (4 folders) (Box 5)
  - Kainen, Dan (contains photographs and handmade cards), 1956-2003, undated, (8 folders) (Box 5)
  - Kainen, Paul (contains handmade cards), 1956-2002, undated, (8 folders) (Box 5)
  - Kainen, Robert, 1977-1995 (Box 5)
  - Kainen, Ruth Cole (contains letters to Jacob Kainen), 1968-1974, undated (Box 5)
  - Kainen, Sy, 1954-1994, undated (Box 5)
  - Kainen, Virginia, 1993-2002, undated (Box 5)
  - Kantor, Lou, 1936-1964, undated, (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Karn, Lynn: see Lowman, Lynn Karn (Box 5)
  - Kaplan, Ruth, 1982-1993, undated (Box 6)
  - Kimmelman, Peter, 1992-1999 (Box 6)
  - Kleinholz, Frank, 1943-1972 (Box 6)
  - Kokkinen, Eila, 1969-1978 (Box 6)
  - Koston, Dina (see also Theater Chamber Players of Kennedy Center), 1997-2002 (Box 6)
  - Krasnow, Iris, 1980-2001, undated (Box 6)
  - Kucera, Greg, 1987-1988, undated (Box 6)
  - Kurosaki, Akira, 1975-1978 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous K: Kainen-Karpinski, 1943-2000, undated (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous K: Kellogg-Knox, 1954-2002, undated (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous K: Kogod-Kuspit, 1957-2001, undated (Box 6)
  - Lab School of Washington, 1990-1996, undated (Box 6)
  - Laget, Mokha, 1988-1993, undated (Box 6)
  - Landau, David, 1983-1995 (Box 6)
  - Landfall Press Inc., 1972-2002 (Box 6)
  - Lapinski, Tadeusz (contains handmade cards), 1968-1984, undated, (5 folders) (Box 6)
  - Lehrer, Ruth Fine: see Fine, Ruth (Box 6)
  - Leiter, Andrew B., 1999-2000 (Box 6)
  - Lerner, Al, 1985-1995 (Box 6)
  - Lesser, Rudi, 1951-1991, undated (Box 6)
  - Levin, Harry G., 1968-1998, undated, (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Levy, David C. (see also Corcoran Gallery of Art), 1991-2002 (Box 6)
  - Lewis, Golda, 1971-1995 (Box 6)
  - Lewis, Jo Ann, 1976-2002 (Box 6)
  - Lewis, Karen, 1980-2001, undated, (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Library of Congress, 1981-1997 (Box 6)
  - Los Angeles County Museum of Art, 1984-1995, (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Lowe, Harry, 1973-1994, undated (Box 6)
  - Lowman, Lynn Karn, 1975-1990, undated, (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Lozowich, Mrs. Adele, 1974-1994 (Box 6)
  - Lunn, Harry, Jr., 1970-1998, undated, (3 folders) (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous L: Landau-Leich, 1955-1999, undated (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous L: Leigman-Levy, 1944-1999, undated (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous L: Lewison-Lowy, 1954-1993, undated (Box 6)
  - Mandle, Roger, 1989-1998 (Box 6)
  - Markel, Kathryn, 1974-1989 (Box 6)
  - Marquardt, Virginia H., 1980-1983 (Box 6)
  - Martha White Gallery, 1982-1984, undated (Box 6)
  - Martin, Richard, 1976-1992 (Box 6)
  - Maryland Art Place, 1990-1991 (Box 6)
  - Maryland School of Art and Design, 1973, undated (Box 6)
  - Mason, Arthur, Esq., 1974-1993 (Box 6)
  - Mattatuck Museum, 1963-2001, undated, (4 folders) (Box 6)
  - McCosh, David and Anne, 1963-2000 (Box 6)
  - McCulloch, Frank and Edie, 1975-1994 (Box 6)
  - McNeil, George, 1946-1995, undated, (4 folders) (Box 6)
  - McPherson, Mr. and Mrs. William, 1976-2002, undated (Box 6)
  - Memorial Service, 2001, undated, (3 folders) (Box 6)
  - Meredith Long Contemporary, 1979-1996, undated (Box 6)
  - Metropolitan Museum of Art (see also Walker, William B.), 1973-1998 (Box 6)
  - Middendorf Gallery, 1977-1994, undated, (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Millard, Charles W., 1986-1997 (Box 6)
  - Millon, Hank and Judy, 1990-2002 (Box 6)
  - Montgomery College, 1979-2000, undated (Box 6)
  - Moore, Mrs. Keiko H., 1976-2001 (Box 6)
  - Morrison, Keith, 1983-1985, undated (Box 6)
  - Morse, Peter, 1968-1993, undated, (3 folders) (Box 7)
  - Muhlert, Jan K., 1976-1985, undated (Box 7)
  - Müller, Hans and Hildi, 1977-1983, undated (Box 7)
  - Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, 1989-1995 (Box 7)
  - Museum of Modern Art, 1973-1997, undated (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous M: MacDonald-McClelland, 1954-1998, undated (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous M: McClintic-Meyerowitz, 1954-1992, undated (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous M: Miceh-Morella, 1944-2002, undated (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous M: Morgan-Myers, 1943-1997, undated (Box 7)
  - National Collection of Fine Arts: see Smithsonian American Art Museum (Box 7)
  - National Gallery of Art (see also Fine, Ruth), 1944-2003, undated, (19 folders) (Box 7)
  - National Museum of American Art: see Smithsonian American Art Museum (Box 7)
  - National Museum of American History, 1986-2001, (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - National Museum of Women in the Arts, 1982-2001, undated, (3 folders) (Box 7)
  - National Portrait Gallery (see also Fern, Alan and Lois), 2001-2003 (Box 7)
  - Nelson-Atkins Museum of Art, 1986-1995 (Box 7)
  - New Art Examiner, 1986-1989, undated (Box 7)
  - New Gallery of Contemporary Art, 1978-1991, undated, (3 folders) (Box 7)
  - Nordland, Gerald, 1966-1998, undated, (5 folders) (Box 7)
  - Northrup, C. Van, 1979-1988, undated, (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Nouvelles de l'Estampe, 1988-1991, undated (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous N: Naifeh-New Republic, 1964-2002, undated (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous N: New York Review-Nunnally, 1977-2001, undated (Box 7)
  - Oberhuber, Konrad, 1976-1991, undated (Box 7)
  - O'Connell, George, 1974-1992, undated (Box 7)
  - O'Connor, Francis V., 1967-1997, undated, (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Orbeck, Jay, 1973-1997, undated, (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Ortner, Mary, 1980-1981 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous O: Oebser-Ostroff, 1954-1993, undated (Box 7)
  - Pace, Stephen and Pamela, 1986-1999 (Box 7)
  - Pacific Northwest College of Art (see also Gilkey, Gordon W.), 1989-2001, undated (Box 7)
  - Parkhurst, Charles, 1975-1999, undated, (3 folders) (Box 7)
  - Parties, 1977-1989, undated, (3 folders) (Box 7)
  - Perlow, Katharina Rich, 1999-2003, undated (Box 8)
  - Phillips, Mrs. Agnes Gorky: see Fielding, Mrs. A.W. (Box 8)
  - Phillips, Matt, 1971-1999, undated (Box 8)
  - Phillips Collection, 1979-1999, undated, (5 folders) (Box 8)
  - Picard, Ben M., 1974-1985 (Box 8)
  - Pielage, Jozef, 1961-1980 (Box 8)
  - Pink, Marilyn, 1978-2001, undated, (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - Pirog, John, 1981 (Box 8)
  - Pollack, Jerome, 1943-2001, undated, (4 folders) (Box 8)
  - Portland Art Museum, 1974-2003, undated, (8 folders) (Box 8)
  - Powell, Richard J., 1988-1996, (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - Prather, Marla, 1990-2001, undated (Box 8)
  - Pratt Institute, 1969-2000, undated, (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - Preilipper, Klaus, 1978-1995 (Box 8)
  - Press, Alan and Dorothy, 1978-1987, undated (Box 8)
  - Print Collector's Newsletter, 1973-1995 (Box 8)
  - Print Council of America, 1981-2000 (Box 8)
  - Purcell, Ann, 1981-1996, undated, (3 folders) (Box 8)
  - Pyramid Atlantic, 1988-1995 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous P: Pakistan American Cultural Centre-Petrone, 1953-2001, undated (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous P: Phillips Memorial Gallery-Pyritz, 1942-2002, undated (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous Q: Queens Museum-Quiroz, 1979-2003 (Box 8)
  - Rahman, Mira, 1976-1990, undated (Box 8)
  - Rand, Archie, 1979-1989, undated (Box 8)
  - Rand, Harry, 1978-2002, undated, (5 folders) (Box 8)
  - Recommendations, 1950-1994, undated, (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - Remington, Gale, 1961-1963, undated (Box 8)
  - Renan, Doris, 1984-1996 (Box 8)
  - Reynolds, Jock, 1984-2002, undated, (9 folders) (Box 8)
  - Riabov, George, 1976-1989, undated (Box 8)
  - Richard, Paul, 1975-1998 (Box 8)
  - Ries, Martin, 1993-2000, undated (Box 8)
  - Robbins, Warren M., 1973-1994, undated (Box 8)
  - Rodwin, Lloyd, 1977-1995 (Box 8)
  - Romero, Enrique, 1977-1982 (Box 8)
  - Ronald Reagan Washington National Airport, 1994-1996, undated, (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - Rosenberg, Harold, 1969-1979 (Box 9)
  - Rosenberg, Sam, 1971-1979 (Box 9)
  - Rosenthal, Mark, 1994-1996 (Box 9)
  - Ross, Betty, 1979-1985, undated (Box 9)
  - Rudd, Eric, 1981-1998 (Box 9)
  - Rutgers University (see also Cate, Phillip Dennis), 1991-2002 (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous R: Rackus-Rewald, 1953-1997, undated (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous R: Reynolts-Rose, 1943-1994, undated (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous R: Rosenbaum-Rutberg, 1950-2001, undated (Box 9)
  - Sachs, Sidney, 1979-1980, undated (Box 9)
  - Saint Louis Art Museum, 1992-1994 (Box 9)
  - Saz, Ruth, 1978-1979, undated (Box 9)
  - Schaar, Eckhard, 1976-1980, undated (Box 9)
  - Schrag, Karl (contains handmade cards), 1987-1995 (Box 9)
  - Scott, David, 1967-2000 (Box 9)
  - Selle, Carol, 1979-1982, undated (Box 9)
  - Shestack, Alan, 1978-2001, undated (Box 9)
  - Simms, Richard A., 1997-1998 (Box 9)
  - Sir Deutsch Gallery, 1981-1990 (Box 9)
  - Smithsonian American Art Museum (see also Broun, Elizabeth), 1966-2002, undated, (19 folders) (Box 9)
  - Smithsonian Institution, 1942-1994, undated, (3 folders) (Box 9)
  - Smithsonian Institution Loyalty Board, 1942-1954, undated (Box 9)
  - Smithsonian Institution Resident Associate Program, 1989-1992, undated (Box 9)
  - Solman, Joseph, 1954-1998, undated (Box 9)
  - Soto, Ofelia, 1978-1986 (Box 9)
  - Southeastern Center for Contemporary Art, 1979-1989, undated (Box 9)
  - Southern Graphics Council, 1996-2002, undated (Box 9)
  - Soyer, Raphael, 1964-2000 (Box 9)
  - Spender, Matthew, 1994-2000, undated (Box 9)
  - Stasik, Andrew, 1968-2001, undated (Box 9)
  - Steinberg, Dr. Leo, 1979-2001, undated, (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - Strick, Jeremy and Wendy, 1988-1999 (Box 9)
  - Sundell, Michael G. and Nina, 1977-1999, undated, (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - Sutherland, David, 1982-1994, undated (Box 9)
  - Swift, Mary, 1975-1999 (Box 9)
  - Syracuse University, 1982-1995 (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous S: Sachs-Schenck, 1953-2000, undated (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous S: Schlesinger-Shiff, 1974-2001, undated (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous S: Sidwell-Solinger, 1959-2001, undated (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous S: Spanierman-Symmes, 1977-2002, undated (Box 9)
  - Tamarind Institute, 1979-1999, undated (Box 9)
  - Taylor, Lisa, 1975-1994, undated (Box 9)
  - Taylor, Prentiss, 1956-2002, undated, (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - Tejera, Victorino, 1959-1994, undated, (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - Theater Chamber Players of Kennedy Center, 1985-1997, undated, (2 folders) (Box 10)
  - Thorton, Valerie, 1979-1996, undated, (2 folders) (Box 10)
  - Tighe, Mary Ann S., 1973-1993, undated (Box 10)
  - Travis, Isabelle Dervaux, 1988-1991 (Box 10)
  - Truitt, Anne, 1993-1999 (Box 10)
  - Tunick, David, 1979-1992 (Box 10)
  - Tyler, Francine, 1988-1992 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous T: Taggart-Thrash, 1956-2000, undated (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous T: Tobias-Tydlacka, 1975-1995, undated (Box 10)
  - University of Maryland, 1963-1996, undated (Box 10)
  - University of Oregon, 1966-2001, undated, (3 folders) (Box 10)
  - University of Pittsburgh, 1965-1979 (Box 10)
  - Upton, Richard, 1969-1997, undated (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous U: Underwood-Ury, 1939-1990, undated (Box 10)
  - Veinus, Abraham, 1944-2001, undated, (3 folders) (Box 10)
  - Veinus, Peter S., 1983-1984, undated (Box 10)
  - Vigtel, Gudmund, 1983-1990 (Box 10)
  - Vivian and Gordon W. Gilkey Center for Graphic Arts: see Gordon, Gilkey W. (Box 10)
  - Vogel, Joseph, 1979-1995, undated (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous V: Vaghi-Vienna Arts Society, Inc., 1977-2002, undated (Box 10)
  - Walker, Barry, 1974-1998 (Box 10)
  - Walker, William B., 1975-1993 (Box 10)
  - Wang, Ming, 1974-2000, undated (Box 10)
  - Washington Moscow Art Exchange, 1988-1990, undated (Box 10)
  - Washington National Airport: see Ronald Reagan Washington National Airport (Box 10)
  - Washington Post, 1978-2003, undated (Box 10)
  - Washington Print Club, 1986-1997, undated (Box 10)
  - Washington Project for the Arts (see also Reynolds, Jock), 1975-1995, undated, (3 folders) (Box 10)
  - Waterbury Hall of Fame, 1996-1998, undated (Box 10)
  - Wayne, June, 1983-2000 (Box 10)
  - Weber, Joanne (contains handmade cards), 1957-2000, undated, (2 folders) (Box 10)
  - Wenniger, Mary Ann, 1976-1983, undated (Box 10)
  - Weintraub, Jacob and Barbara, 1979-1993 (Box 10)
  - Weissman, Julian, 1981-2003, undated (Box 10)
  - Whitehead, John and Nancy, 1994-1997, undated (Box 10)
  - Whitney Museum of American Art, 1972-1996, undated (Box 10)
  - Whyte, Angus, 1973-1990, undated (Box 10)
  - William A. Farnsworth Library and Art Museum, 1983-1985, undated (Box 10)
  - Williams, Mr. and Mrs. Dave H., 1986-1999, undated (Box 10)
  - Winter, Ann, 1959-1962, undated (Box 10)
  - Works Progress Administration, 1944-1995, undated (Box 10)
  - Wright, Richard, 1982-2001, undated (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous W: Wackers-Watrous, 1946-2002, undated (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous W: Wattenmaker-White, 1952-2002, undated (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous W: Wiener-World, 1949-2000, undated (Box 10)
  - Yale University (see also Field, Richard S.), 1983-2003 (Box 10)
  - Young, Gene, 1997-2002, undated (Box 10)
  - Yourieva, Mrs. Tatiana, 1978-1997, undated (Box 10)
  - Yunker, Adja, 1948-1990, undated (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous Y: Yanosky-Young, 1976-1990, undated (Box 10)
  - Zabriskie Gallery, 1974-1981 (Box 10)
  - Zevin, Lillian, 1978-1993 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous Z: Zerner-Zierler, 1969-1993 (Box 10)
- Writings, 1939-2002, undated, Series 3:; (Boxes 10-11; 0.6 linear feet)
  The series contains writings by and about Jacob Kainen. Writings by Jacob Kainen include articles, essays, introductions to exhibition catalogs, lectures, statements, short stories as well as lists, notes, and rough drafts of speeches and essays. Also included are lectures given by Jacob Kainen. Writings by others contain essays, a thesis, and a dissertation about Jacob Kainen.
  The series has been divided into two subseries:
  3.1: Writings by Jacob Kainen, 1946-1995, undated
  3.2: Writings about Jacob Kainen, 1972-2002, undated
  - Writings by Jacob Kainen, 1946-1995, undated, 3.1:
    Writings by Jacob Kainen include essays about Arshile Gorky, Raphael Soyer, John Dowell, and the Works Progress Administration. Mainstream art, New York in the 1930s, and art in the 1930s are topics addressed in the lectures included in this series. The subseries is arranged alphabetically by type of material and chronologically under each heading.
    - Articles and Essays, 1966-1968, undated, (2 folders) (Box 10)
    - Exhibition Catalogs, 1953-1986, undated (Box 10)
    - Lectures, 1978-1988, (6 folders) (Box 10)
    - Lists, 1964-1988, undated (Box 10)
    - Notes, 1946-1995, undated, (2 folders) (Box 10)
    - Rough Drafts, 1976-1995, undated, (2 folders) (Box 10)
    - Short Stories, undated, (2 folders) (Box 10)
    - Statements, 1952-1989, undated (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous, 1939-2000, undated, (2 folders) (Box 10)
  - Writings about Jacob Kainen, 1972-2002, undated, 3.2:
    The subseries contains writings about Jacob Kainen's painting, the Graphic Arts Division of the Works Progress Administration, the Smithsonian Institution's Division of Graphic Arts, and Jacob Kainen's art collection. The subseries is arranged alphabetically by the author's last name and chronologically under each heading.
    - Berman, Avis, 1992, (4 folders) (Box 11)
    - Griffiths, Antony V., undated (Box 11)
    - Holladay, Winton Smoot, 1974, (7 folders) (Box 11)
    - Kainen, Ruth Cole, 1972-2002 (Box 11)
    - Maxfield, David, undated (Box 11)
    - Seaton, Elizabeth Gaede, 2000, (8 folders) (Box 11)
- Diaries, 1952-2002, undated, Series 4:; (Box 11; 0.5 linear feet)
  The series includes more informal writings by Jacob Kainen: diary entries, journal entries, and two notebooks from Jacob's European trips in 1956 and 1962. The notebooks were removed from their original binders for preservation purposes. Ruth Cole Kainen's extensive diary entries about Jacob Kainen, which consist of fragments and complete entries, are also included in this series. A large portion of Mrs. Kainen's diary entries deal with Jacob Kainen's two sons and with his retrospectives. The series is arranged alphabetically by type of material and chronologically under each heading.
  - Diary Entries, 1952-1993 (Box 11)
  - Dismantled Notebook, 1956, (4 folders) (Box 11)
  - Dismantled Notebook, 1962, (3 folders) (Box 11)
  - Journal Entries (contains three drawings by Jacob Kainen), 1952-1954, undated (Box 11)
  - Ruth Cole Kainen Diary Entries, 1975-2002, (31 folders) (Box 11)
- Calendars, 1972-2001, Series 5:; (Boxes 11-12; 0.6 linear feet)
  The series includes daily calendars, consisting of actual calendar pages and typed schedules, and itineraries from Jacob and Ruth's various trips abroad. Many of the calendars are incomplete with certain months and years missing. The daily calendars also contain notes and lists relating to the events planned on specific days. The series is arranged alphabetically by type of material and chronologically under each heading.
  - Daily Calendars, 1974-1990, (15 folders) (Box 11)
  - Daily Calendars, 1991-2001, (21 folders) (Box 12)
  - Travel Itineraries, 1972-1996, (2 folders) (Box 12)
- Transcripts, 1972-1994, undated, Series 6:; (Boxes 12-13; 0.7 linear feet)
  Transcripts of formal interviews, informal dialogues, discussions, and conversations are included in the series. The transcripts cover topics concerning Jacob's biography, his artwork, and art history in general. Many transcripts include explanatory notes and introductions written by Ruth Cole Kainen. Some of the transcripts are incomplete with missing pages. In other cases, there are different versions of the same conversations.
  This series is divided into two subseries:
  6.1: Conversations, 1975-1994
  6.2: Interviews, 1977-1992, undated
  - Conversations, 1975-1994, 6.1:
    The subseries includes transcriptions of informal dinner conversations, telephone conversations, discussions, and dialogues between Jacob Kainen and others. The transcripts filed under Ruth Cole Kainen are conversations strictly between herself and Jacob Kainen and comprise the bulk of the subseries. However, many of the conversations with the other participants include comments from both Jacob and Ruth Kainen. The subseries is arranged alphabetically by the primary participant's last name and chronologically under each heading.
    - Berman, Avis, 1993 (Box 12)
    - Donovan, Bobby, 1984 (Box 12)
    - Hayter, S.W., 1976 (Box 12)
    - Hopps, Walter, 1991-1992 (Box 12)
    - Kainen, Ruth Cole, 1975-1994, (29 folders) (Box 12)
    - Rand, Harry, 1978-1991 (Box 12)
    - Rand, Harry and Jennifer Gibson, 1981, (2 folders) (Box 12)
    - Sundell, Michael, 1978 (Box 12)
    - Taylor, Dr. Joshua, 1976 (Box 12)
    - Veinus, Peter, 1984 (Box 12)
    - Walker, Barry, 1988 (Box 12)
  - Interviews, 1977-1992, undated, 6.2:
    The subseries includes transcripts of formal interviews with Jacob Kainen concerning such topics as Mark Rothko, Alma Thomas, American Printmaking, and Washington art. As with the previous subseries, the transcripts include comments from Ruth Cole Kainen in addition to those by Jacob Kainen. The subseries is organized alphabetically by interviewer's last name and chronologically under each heading.
    - Berman, Avis, 1982 (Box 12)
    - Blair, Ann, 1977 (Box 12)
    - Brodsky, Marian, 1990 (Box 12)
    - Field, Richard, 1982, (3 folders) (Box 12)
    - Green, Sue, 1985 (Box 12)
    - Hood, Richard, 1984 (Box 12)
    - Ingram, Elliot, undated (Box 12)
    - Johnson, Barbara Martin and Clarissa Wittenburg, 1978 (Box 12)
    - Krasnow, Iris, 1989 (Box 12)
    - Maskery, Mary Ann, 1977 (Box 12)
    - Morrison, Keith, 1984 (Box 12)
    - Perlmutter, Jack, 1980 (Box 13)
    - Richard, Paul, 1985 (Box 13)
    - Ross, Betty, 1982 (Box 13)
    - Sundell, Michael, 1978, (2 folders) (Box 13)
    - Sundell, Michael and Alison Abelson, 1980 (Box 13)
    - Swift, Mary, 1992 (Box 13)
    - Tannous, David, 1978 (Box 13)
    - Travis, Isabelle, 1988, (2 folders) (Box 13)
    - Wilson, Judith, 1978, (2 folders) (Box 13)
    - Miscellaneous Transcripts, 1977-1993 (Box 13)
- Inventories, 1927-1999, Series 7:; (Box 13; 0.7 linear feet)
  General and specific inventories of paintings by Jacob Kainen comprise the series. The inventories were originally contained in eight labeled binders. Although dismantled for preservation reasons, the original titles of the binders and original order of the pages have been preserved. Color photographs of Kainen's paintings accompany many of the inventory entries.
  - Painting Inventory, 1927-1949, (4 folders) (Box 13)
  - Painting Inventory, 1969-1975, (4 folders) (Box 13)
  - Painting Inventory, 1976-1980, (3 folders) (Box 13)
  - Painting Inventory, 1984-1988, (4 folders) (Box 13)
  - Paintings Sold or Missing, 1927-1953, (5 folders) (Box 13)
  - Paintings Sold or Missing, 1968-1983, (5 folders) (Box 13)
  - Unsold Paintings, 1981-1983, (5 folders) (Box 13)
  - Unsold Paintings, 1989-1999, (3 folders) (Box 13)